{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Along with Henry David Thoreau, this thinker was cited as the chief Western influence on\nGandhi. His pacifist tome The Kingdom of God is Within You made him the leader of dissenting\nChristians in early twentieth century Russia. For 10 points, name this man who viewed his\ntheological work as more important than his novels, such as Anna Karenina. ",
      "answer": [
        "Leo Tolstoy",
        "Tolstoy",
        "Leo Nikolayevich Tolstoy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Karl Jaspers (pr. YOS-perz) is often called a Christian philosopher within this framework.\nThis philosophy was dubbed \"a humanism\" in a book by one of its major exponents, who also\nwrote Roads to Freedom. For 10 points, identify this philosophy originated by Soren\nKierkegaard and popularized by Jean-Paul Sartre (pr. SART) in which humans must create\nmeaning in the universe.",
      "answer": [
        "existentialism",
        "existential"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Marc Dubois suffered from this condition as the pilot of Air France Flight 447, which crashed in 2009.\nWorld records for this condition are no longer maintained due to fear of harm, but the last scientifically\ndocumented record for this condition is Randy Gardner’s 264 hours. Tracy Morgan was injured in a\nbus accident caused by a Walmart truck driver suffering from this condition. For ten points, name this\ncondition that causes irritability and yawning.",
      "answer": [
        "sleep deprivation",
        "insomnia",
        "fatigue",
        "exhaustion",
        "tiredness",
        "lack of sleep"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Malcolm Gladwell’s The Tipping Point discusses how this city’s rate of violent crimes was decreased\nby stricter rules on minor crimes, as predicted by “broken window” theory. In 1964, Winston Moseley shot\na woman from this city who was unable to get help despite several onlookers. For ten points, name this\ncity where the bystander effect led to Kitty Genovese’s death in its borough of Queens.",
      "answer": [
        "New York City",
        "New York",
        "NYC"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This field of research was what John McCarthy was working on when he invented the LISP\nprogramming language in 1959. This field of research is the subject of John Searle's \"Chinese\nRoom\" argument and is divided into \"weak\" and \"strong\" branches. For 10 points, name this\nfield which seeks to duplicate functions of the human brain on computers.",
      "answer": [
        "artificial intelligence",
        "AI"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This thinker explained a cultural absence of rape and jealousy, as well as overall lower levels of stress,\nby noting a casual social view regarding sexuality. Derek Freeman controversially criticized this thinker’s\nstudy of adolescent females on the Pacific island of Ta’u, which she visited while studying under Franz\nBoas. For ten points, name this American anthropologist, the author of Coming of Age in Samoa.",
      "answer": [
        "Margaret Mead",
        "Mead"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A work about these people is divided into sections concerning “History,” “Psychology,” and “Biology”\nand argues that these people have become a passive “Other.” One philosopher distinguished these people\nfrom barbarians and the uneducated to argue for their suffrage. J.S. Mill wrote about the Subjection of,\nfor ten points, name what group of people, the subjects of Simone Beauvoir’s The Second Sex?",
      "answer": "women"
    },
    {
      "question": "George Miller’s work on this process and its “magic number” was criticized by later experiments\nthat demonstrated the value of “chunking” in this process. The ancient Greek and Roman “method of\nloci” was used to improve this process, and autistic savants are frequently mentioned for their ability to\nperform extreme feats of this process. For ten points, name this mental process that consists of encoding,\nstoring, and retrieving information about past events.",
      "answer": "memory"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these policies named for Walker improved relations with Great Britain after the repeal of the\nCorn Laws. One of these policies was described as an abomination and led to the Nullification Crisis, while\nthe Smoot-Hawley example made the Great Depression worse by slowing global trade. NAFTA restricts\nCanada, Mexico, and the United States from using, for ten points, what type of tax on imported goods?",
      "answer": [
        "tariff",
        "Walker Tariff",
        "Tariff of Abominations",
        "Smoot-Hawley Tariff"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Margaret Thatcher claimed to have carried a copy of this man’s most famous work in her handbag\nat all times. This thinker rejects the “benevolence of the butcher, baker, and brewer” as the reason that\ndinner is expected and, in his most famous work, describes a metaphor about the unintended social\nbenefits of private, selfish actions as the “invisible hand.” For ten points, name this Scottish “Father of\nEconomics,” the author of The Wealth of Nations.",
      "answer": [
        "Adam Smith",
        "Smith"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The over-creation of these parts of speech through the use of derivational morphology creates their\n“zombie” type. Socrates defined these parts of speech as “onoma” in the Cratylus. Classifiers on these\ntypes of speech are found in Chinese and Turkish to add quantifiers. Articles are sometimes placed before\nthese parts of speech in English in order to start a type of “phrase” contrasted with verb phrases. For ten\npoints, name this part of speech, often defined as including persons, places, things, or ideas.",
      "answer": "nouns"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Ford administration declared this phenomenon \"public enemy number one\" and circulated\nbuttons which encouraged Americans to \"whip\" this thing \"now.\" Paul Volcker was instructed by\nthe Reagan administration to get this thing under control at any cost to the unemployment rate.\nFor 10 points, identify this phenomenon of generally rising prices.",
        "answer": "inflation"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Paul Volcker was the chairman of what body, a position later held by Alan Greenspan?",
        "answer": "Federal Reserve, The Fed, Board of Governors, Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A major advance in this field was formulated by Stanley Jevons and William Marshall in the\n1880s. This field's dominant textbook in postwar America was written by Paul Samuelson, who\nsubscribed to the ideas formulated by John Maynard Keynes. For 10 points, name this social\nscience which uses supply and demand curves to study financial decision-making.",
        "answer": "economics"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Keynes's The Economic Consequences of the Peace warned that the World War I\nreparations payments imposed on what country were too harsh?",
        "answer": [
          "Germany",
          "Weimar Republic"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "When setting up skeletons of this species for display, museums frequently used the skull of\nCamarasaurus. That practice perpetuated Othniel Charles Marsh's belief that this species was not\nidentical to a skeleton unearthed in 1885. For 10 points, identify this dinosaur species which\nMarsh erroneously identified as separate from the fictitious \"brontosaurus.\"",
        "answer": "apatosaurus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The apatosaurus flourished during what middle period of the Mesozoic era?",
        "answer": [
          "Jurassic Period",
          "Jurassic"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Nicholas Reeves has controversially suggested using radar in this location to find hidden rooms. Pierre\nLacau supervised a study of this location funded by Lord Carnavon who died of mosquito-borne disease\nshortly after it was opened. This location, officially designated KV62, was discovered in 1922 by Howard\nCarter. For ten points, name this surprisingly well-preserved burial site of a boy pharaoh.",
        "answer": [
          "the tomb of King Tutankhamun",
          "tomb Tut",
          "Crypt Tut",
          "Burial site Tut",
          "Tomb of Tutankhamun"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "King Tut’s tomb, like numerous other pharaoh tombs, was discovered in this Egyptian valley\nacross the Nile River from Thebes.",
        "answer": [
          "Valley of the Kings",
          "Kings"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Interahamwe engaged in one of these events after the death of Juvenal Habyarimana. Viktor\nYuschenko classified the Holodomor as one of these events, as the Soviets declared the possession of food\na crime. Turkey does not recognize one of these events against the Armenian people. For ten points, name\nthese atrocities that involve mass killings of a specific demographic, such as the Holocaust.",
        "answer": "genocide"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Holodomor was a massive famine in this former Soviet republic, which saw the Orange\nRevolution oust Viktor Yanukovych in favor of Victor Yushchenko in 2005.",
        "answer": "Ukraine"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The price elasticity of this quantity should always be negative, but Veblen goods violate that theory.\nJohn Maynard Keynes argued that, in recessions, the aggregate of this quantity should be bolstered by\ngovernment spending. During the Irish Potato Famine, this quantity rose for potatoes even as their price\nrose, as people could no longer afford luxuries like meat. For ten points, name this economic quantity\nthat, in competitive markets, should reach equilibrium with supply.",
        "answer": "demand"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A demand shock may be triggered by these events, such as one passed by President Bush in 2001\nand made permanent for most Americans in wake of the 2012 fiscal cliff.",
        "answer": [
          "tax cuts"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man noted that “The clock cannot be set back. You cannot restore Central Europe to 1870” in\na work that lamented Clemenceau’s “Carthaginian Peace.” This author of The Economic Consequences\nof the Peace argued that natural business cycles should be moderated by government intervention. For\nten points, name this British economist who outlined modern macroeconomics with his General Theory\nof Employment, Interest, and Money.",
        "answer": [
          "John Maynard Keynes",
          "Keynes"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This New York Times columnist and modern Keynesian thinker won the 2008 Economics Nobel\nPrize as his theories of international trade were being tested in the recovery from the Great Recession.",
        "answer": [
          "Paul Krugman",
          "Krugman"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Corona program was created to perform this action from outer space. Klaus Fuchs was a scientist\nwho performed this action. In 1960, Gary Powers was shot down while attempting to perform this action\nin a U2 plane whose cameras were recovered by the Soviets. For ten points, name this type of covert action\nperformed by the CIA against the Soviet Union during the Cold War to gain information.",
        "answer": [
          "spying",
          "espionage"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Julius and Ethel, a married couple with this last name, were executed in 1953 after being\nconvicted of spying for the Soviet Union.",
        "answer": "the Rosenbergs"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Claims made about a social class in this work were later revised in its author’s Theories of Surplus\nValue. This work introduces the concept of historical materialism. A “holy alliance” created to “exorcise\nthis specter” is the focus of the first section of this work, which concludes by calling for the “workers of\nthe world” to “unite!.” For ten points, name this 1848 political pamphlet co-written by Friedrich Engels\nand Karl Marx.",
        "answer": "The Communist Manifesto"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Marx’s idea that history repeats itself “first as tragedy, then as farce” was written about the\ncoup of this historical figure, the nephew of an earlier French dictator with a much more successful coup.",
        "answer": [
          "Napoleon III",
          "Louis-Napoleon"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One work about this phenomenon uses the research of Adolph Wagner and Henry Morselli and\nstates that it can be caused by “excessive individuation” or oppressive discipline. A work titled for this\nphenomenon theorized that differences in social integration caused this to be more common in Protestants\nthan in Catholics. This phenomenon was separated into altruistic, egoistic, and fatalistic types in a famous\ncase study by Emile [ay-meel] Durkheim. For ten points, name this oft-studied tragic human behavior,\nthe ending of one’s own life.",
        "answer": "suicide"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Durkheim argued that a fourth form of suicide is motivated by this phenomenon, characterized\nby a lack of social direction and moral confusion.",
        "answer": "anomie"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man died before completing the “Tenth Walk” portion of his Reveries of a Solitary Walker. This\nauthor’s epistolary novel about two lovers at the foot of the Alps was the best-selling novel of the 18th\ncentury. This man’s two submissions to the Academy of Dijon constituted his Discourse on the Arts and\nSciences and Discourse on Inequality, which develop his ideas of the “noble savage.” For ten points, name\nthis French Enlightenment philosopher who contrasted life under government with the ideal community\nof man living in nature in his The Social Contract.",
        "answer": [
          "Jean-Jacques Rousseau",
          "Rousseau"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "According to Rousseau, this specific concept was equal to the rule of law. Rousseau’s Discourse\non Political Economy reflected his idea that this concept was actually a defense for the individual against\nthe masses.",
        "answer": "the general will"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these systems was invented in the 15th century by Sejong the Great of the Joseon Dynasty; its\n40 elements can be combined into over 11 thousand blocks. The oldest of these systems is an abjad with\n22 entries; that Phoenician system inspired modern examples such as Greek, Cyrillic, and Latin. The first\ntwo entries in the Hebrew system inspires the name of, for ten points, what term for a set of letters used\nto write a language?",
        "answer": "alphabet"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Sejong the Great invented hangul, the alphabet for this Asian language. It was spoken in the\nJoseon dynasty, and it has undergone significant changes over the last 70 years after the splitting of the\ntwo countries in which it is primarily spoken.",
        "answer": [
          "Korean language",
          "Korean",
          "Korea",
          "South Korea",
          "North Korea",
          "South and North Korea"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A news photographer captured an assault on Richard Frankensteen, a leader of this\nunion, by surrendering fake photo plates. This union, now led by Dennis Williams,\nrepresents many (20 pts) ",
        "graduate students. This union, which operated a dedicated radio\nstation, was involved in the \"Battle of the (10 pts) ",
        "Overpass\" during its leadership by Walter\nReuther. The 1937 Flint sit-down strike gave it official recognition. For 10 points, name this\nunion of car industry employees."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "UAW",
        "United Automobile Workers",
        "United Auto Workers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) When this phenomenon is enacted to target negative externalities, it is known as\n\"Pigouvian\" (pr. pig-OO-vee-uhn). According to supply-side economics, this process produces\nsimilar (20 pts) ",
        "revenues at the extremes, as demonstrated by the Laffer curve. A slogan in the\nAmerican revolution decried the imposition of this process (10 pts) ",
        "\"without representation.\" For 10\npoints, identify this process in which the government legally compels people to provide money."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "taxation",
        "tax"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Fossils of this species were first found in the Engis Caves of Belgium, though they get\ntheir name from subsequent finds on the outskirts of Dusseldorf in a namesake (20 pts) ",
        "valley.\nThis species was once believed to have been rendered extinct by bands of rock-throwing\npredators, though it is now known from DNA markers that they (10 pts) ",
        "interbred with the\nancestors of modern humans. For 10 points, name this large-skulled hominid which survived in\nEurope until 40,000 BC."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Neanderthals"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) To show that the Federal Reserve's contractionary economic policy exacerbated the\nGreat Depression, this man collaborated with Anna Schwartz on A (20 pts) ",
        "Monetary History of\nthe United States. He popularized his ideas on the relationship between the free market and\nindividual liberty in the PBS miniseries Free to Choose. (10 pts) ",
        "For 10 points, name this leader of\nthe Chicago school of economics who founded monetarism."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Milton Friedman",
        "Friedman"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man collaborated with Morris Halle on the 1968 phonological study The Sound\nPattern of English. That text extended his theory of \"poverty of the (20 pts) ",
        "stimulus,\" or the\ninability of human culture to cause the development of (10 pts) ",
        "language absent a biological role\nin the brain. For 10 points, name this theorist of transformational-generative grammar, an MIT\nlinguist also known for his leadership of the intellectual left wing in the U.S."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Noam Chomsky",
        "Chomsky"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This adjective names a white supremacist “Council of Citizens” led by Earl Holt. Brent\nBozell ghostwrote a book for Arizona Senator Barry Goldwater about The Conscience of\nthis type of person. The Canadian Alliance (20 pts) ",
        "merged with another party to form the\nCanadian political party of this name, which was, until October 2015, led by Stephen (10 pts) ",
        "Harper. Traditional cultural institutions are supported by, for ten points, what political philosophy that\ndescribes the American Republican Party, contrasted with “liberalism”?"
      ],
      "answer": "conservative"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Edwin Guthrie, a researcher in this school of thought, formulated a “one-trial theory”\nthat opposed its founders’ findings. The Premack Principle in this school of thought was\ntested on children using gumballs and pinball machines. Edward (20 pts) ",
        "Thorndike, an early\nproponent of this school of thought, devised his Law of Effect by observing cats figure out\npuzzle boxes. Working within this school of thought, John (10 pts) ",
        "Watson and B. F. Skinner\ntheorized “classical” and “operant” types of conditioning. For ten points, name this school of psychology\nwhich focuses on quantifiable changes in a person’s actions."
      ],
      "answer": "behaviorism"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This tradition was criticized in an 1908 Arthur Lovejoy paper about “The Thirteen [of\nthese],” which accused it of defining “truth” and “belief” ambiguously. The “neo” form of\nthis school was developed by a man who rejected the idea that philosophy should be a (20 pts) ",
        "“mirror of nature,” Richard Rorty. A developer of this school of thought wrote the tract\n“How To Make Our Ideas Clear” about this movement and worked with (10 pts) ",
        "William James on\nits development. For ten points, name this American philosophical tradition, founded by Charles Sanders\nPeirce and named for its focus on the practical effects of thought."
      ],
      "answer": "pragmatism"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one of this man’s studies, he correctly predicted that misplaced envelopes addressed\nto groups like “Friends of the Nazi Party” would be “rescued” less frequently than personal\nletters. The 1961 trial and testimony of Adolf (20 pts) ",
        "Eichmann in Jerusalem inspired this\nman’s experiment in which the command “you must go on” led over one-third of this man’s\nsubjects to administer supposedly (10 pts) ",
        "lethal doses of electricity to test subjects. For ten points,\nname this American psychologist of a controversial obedience experiment."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Stanley Milgram",
        "Milgram"
      ]
    }
  ]
}